<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <title>A11y Dojo</title>
    <link href="https://jsydik.github.io/accessibility-dojo/feed.xml" rel="self" />
    <link href="https://jsydik.github.io/accessibility-dojo" />
    <updated>2020-03-18T04:20:16-05:00</updated>
    <author>
        <name>Jeremy Sydik</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://jsydik.github.io/accessibility-dojo</id>

    <entry>
        <title>Knowing Where One&#x27;s Towel Is</title>
        <author>
            <name>Jeremy Sydik</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://jsydik.github.io/accessibility-dojo/post-3.html"/>
        <id>https://jsydik.github.io/accessibility-dojo/post-3.html</id>

        <updated>2020-03-18T18:00:00-05:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://jsydik.github.io/accessibility-dojo/media/posts/3/EmptyClassroom.jpg" alt="Desks and Chairs in an Empty Classroom" />
                    <p>So you’ve recently “decided” to move your entire semester online under duress in the middle of a global crisis to the tick of a stopwatch—you probably have a few questions.</p>

                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://jsydik.github.io/accessibility-dojo/media/posts/3/EmptyClassroom.jpg" alt="Desks and Chairs in an Empty Classroom" />
                <p>So you’ve recently “decided” to move your entire semester online under duress in the middle of a global crisis to the tick of a stopwatch—you probably have a few questions.</p>

<p>This wasn’t quite how (or when) I expected to be getting back to these articles, but that feeling seems to be going around lately.  This one is going to be about working toward being inclusive and accessible in pieces and parts when everything is stacked against it - the “meatball surgery” of accessible content design so to speak.   This will be about accessibility from the perspective of <em>triage</em> rather than Proper Design as it Should Be, making things as accessible as they need to be today and coming back for the rest as we go.  That’s not to say we won’t defend our ideals - if our approach to equity becomes meaningless in a crisis, it never really meant much to begin with.</p>
<p>First things first, a couple of disclaimers—I mention a few products, but that shouldn’t be construed as an endorsement of their results.  Also, I’m an accessibility professional with over twenty years of experience, but I’m not <em>your institution's</em> accessibility professional. If there is any conflict, those policies, procedures, and processes should lead your practice.</p>
<p>Next, I want you to understand that what’s happening to you right now <em>sucks</em>.  It’s <em>nonsense</em> and you are absolutely right if you feel angry about it. This reality is not the way to provide Good Instructional Design for Distance Learning and it’s unfair to expect it from you (and your students) without prior experience and at best days to prep.</p>
<p>Finally, to borrow the tagline of Douglas Adams’ fine old guide—<em>Don’t Panic</em>.  Things may or not be “okay”, but you’re doing your best. You’re here reading this in spite of the cards you’ve been dealt because, like most instructors I know, you care that much about your students and the things you are teaching them, so let’s see what we can do.</p>
<h2 id="mcetoc_1e3mclsv10">Getting Your Bearings</h2>
<p>To scope your needs you will want to identify which students in your class have accommodations that you need to account for.  You will likely know who these students are and what their accommodations are from your in-classroom semester. For questions about how existing in-class accommodations need to be implemented or modified during transition, the most important thing you can do is to contact your campus student services or ADA offices—you absolutely will not be the first person to ask them.</p>
<p>The goal here is to know which resources you will and won’t need.  For example, if you don’t have anyone in the current term with a text or visual disability, but you do have someone who is deaf or hard of hearing, you will likely be able to put your checks for alternate text on the back burner, but captions or transcripts will be a pressing need and, depending on your institution’s CART captiomer or interpreter availability, there may be restrictions on when or how long you will be able to run synchronous sessions.</p>
<p>The prominent feature of triage is that we’re not going to address every accessibility concern <em>right now</em>.  We’re going to identify what <em>needs</em> to be done <em>right now</em> and address those to keep the ship afloat. I can hear a few of my professional colleagues tensing up right now, so I need to make it absolutely clear—this approach can <strong><em>ONLY</em></strong> be taken for online courses and resources that are only available to the instructor and the current semester’s students.  If you are producing resources for public distribution, they need to be fully accessible in all ways. Given the current reality, my recommendation is to keep your materials locked down at this point and focus on the students you have <em>this</em> semester, After this term and the current crisis is over, you may well wish to get back to classroom-only teaching or you may choose to keep some of these resources available for the long term.  <em>then</em> you can revisit them and fill the remaining gaps needed to make them a reusable resource.</p>
<p>Additionally, you’ll want to check in with all your students if you haven’t already.  They’re facing many of the same sorts of disruptions you are—thrust into an online class that was supposed to be in-person to deal with classroom technologies they’re not familiar with.  Some of them will also be doing it with kids who are now at home with them while their own schools are moving online. They may also be anxious with uncertainties related to their own job changes and/or losses or even of an unexpected move across the city, state, or country.  All of these factors will have their own implications for which technologies you’ll want to use to teach—if large numbers of students are unable to connect at what had been the usual class time, and even if you all chose the in-person classroom for the benefits of synchronous interaction, asynchronous discussion may not only be your only option, it may be the best one for these circumstances.</p>
<h2 id="mcetoc_1e3mcts5r1">Disabilities and Classroom Technology</h2>
<p>Formally, when we talk about disability, we’re meaning a physical or mental impairment to an individual that substantially limits one or more major life activities.  There are many broad categories of disabilities, but for the purposes of digital content, the bulk of your efforts will be focused on visual, auditory, mobility, and cognitive disabilities.</p>
<h3 id="mcetoc_1e3mcu4k32">Visual Disabilities</h3>
<p>Persons who are blind or have low vision will use screen reader or screen magnification software to access and navigate online content.  Two key techniques for accessibility for this group of people will be to make sure any web forms that you create have clear labeling, and to write alternate text for any images and charts you make available.  This text should be focused on <em>your intent</em> as an instructor—don’t get trapped into describing details of the image that weren’t part of why you selected it.</p>
<p>Other people may have average visual acuity but have color blindness or another condition that reduces the ability to distinguish hue or contrast.  While some adjustments can be made from their end, the proper practice is to check images and color selections before using them. Color and contrast can be tested using tools like <a href="https://asada.website/cvsimulator/e/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Chromatic Vision Simulator</a> or <a href="https://developer.paciellogroup.com/resources/contrastanalyser/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Colour Contrast Analyser</a>.</p>
<p>Finally, while it’s not truly a visual issue per se, repetitive content that causes flash or flicker is tremendously dangerous to persons susceptible to photosensitive seizures.  This is a more advanced topic, but suffice it to say, if you find that your videos or other content have a strobe-like effect, don’t use them and seek assistance.</p>
<h3 id="mcetoc_1e3md491d3">Auditory Disabilities</h3>
<p>For classroom purposes, addressing the needs of persons who are deaf or hard of hearing is technically simpler yet more labor intensive comparatively.  Your podcasts or other audio content will require transcripts, your video will require captions, and your live conferencing will need a captioner or sign  interpreter. For all of these, you will want to contact your student services for guidance and availability of resources.</p>
<p>It is important to note that automatic transcription and captioning tools are useful if you don’t have external resources available, but the results are <em>not</em> sufficient and require editing to be accessible.  That said, if you don’t have access or funding for contracted options like <a href="https://www.3playmedia.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">3Play</a>, <a href="http://www.rev.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Rev</a>, or <a href="http://verbit.ai/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Verbit</a>, starting with automatic captions in YouTube or a transcript from <a href="http://otter.ai/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Otter.ai</a> can speed the process tremendously.</p>
<h3 id="mcetoc_1e3mdb92q4">Mobility Disabilities</h3>
<p>For the online classroom, the key things to remember for persons with mobility disabilities will be that they may not be able to use a mouse pointer based interface (or in some cases may require one).  While this will hopefully be handled by your LMS/CMS, it never hurts to try tabbing through any interactive content you create to ensure that it can work mouse-free. It’ll also mean avoiding small or closely spaced images or buttons that would need to be clicked on for those who use eye tracking or have a tremor that makes mouse use possible but difficult.</p>
<h3 id="mcetoc_1e3mdbic85">Cognitive and Psychological Disabilities</h3>
<p>Your students may have a wide variety of cognitive or psychological disabilities that influence how they will interact with your course content, but many of the techniques you’ll need to be aware of are things that you will already know from your in-person classroom experience such as constructing slides and graphics to be clearly perceivable, selecting fonts less likely to interfere with a processing disorder, and so on.  For asynchronous content, you won’t have the opportunity for immediate feedback if your content isn’t clearly understood, so it is important to keep your language clear and straightforward. For synchronized meetings, on the other hand, you will be interacting in real time but still won’t have access to body and facial language or other classroom cues you may be used to, so it may be helpful to be particularly intentional about checking in with your students frequently to verify understanding.</p>
<p>Outside of these, for the purposes of online instruction, the most likely accommodations you’re likely to encounter is flexibility with attendance or assignment due dates, which will be mostly procedural rather than technical (though you should make sure that you’re familiar with how to adjust a due date in your LMS and determine how the student will be able to get access to missed material in this new environment).</p>
<p>So, that’s it?  Well, No. Not at all. But it’s a start.  I’ll be trying to write and update content that explores these issues in more depth in the near future.</p>
<h2 id="mcetoc_1e3mdca286">Act on It!</h2>
<ol>
<li>Communicate with students and disability services as needed to understand their needs and your own.</li>
<li>Contact your campus learning or information technologies group to request access to accessibility guides for online classroom technologies that you plan to use (LMS/CMS, video conferencing, chat, forums, etc).</li>
<li>Beginning with the course content coming up first, begin to build a plan of attack, starting with the absolute minimum that it takes to get the students what you need them to have and building from there.</li>
<li>Practice self care.  This is a marathon, not a sprint, and you’re the leader of your classroom community.  Keeping yourself well is a high priority as well.</li>
</ol>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Principles Before Guidelines</title>
        <author>
            <name>Jeremy Sydik</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://jsydik.github.io/accessibility-dojo/principles-before-guidelines.html"/>
        <id>https://jsydik.github.io/accessibility-dojo/principles-before-guidelines.html</id>

        <updated>2020-03-18T04:19:41-05:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://jsydik.github.io/accessibility-dojo/media/posts/2/JusticeNYC.jpg" alt="Sculpture of Justice at New York City Courthouse" />
                    <p>I prefer to take a <em>principles before guidelines</em> approach to accessibility. Staying focused on compliance issues is a common approach to accessibility, so it may seem surprising that I’m going to push the guidelines out of the way for now.</p>

                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://jsydik.github.io/accessibility-dojo/media/posts/2/JusticeNYC.jpg" alt="Sculpture of Justice at New York City Courthouse" />
                <p>I prefer to take a <em>principles before guidelines</em> approach to accessibility. Staying focused on compliance issues is a common approach to accessibility, so it may seem surprising that I’m going to push the guidelines out of the way for now.</p>

<p>If this concerns you, don’t worry too much—I’ll eventually get to the topic of formal accessibility testing where standards and guidelines rule, and you’ll likely look longingly at these halcyon days.</p>
<p>When we get there, you’ll find that guidelines are important for sorting out details and testing for compliance but they’re not written as instructional documents. Our goal for the moment is helping as many people as possible get the information they want—not learning to be “rules lawyers.” When we add video to our sites, we don’t want to be thinking:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>"Section 508, §1194.24(c) says: All training and informational video and multimedia productions which support the agency’s mission, regardless of format, that contain speech or other audio information necessary for the comprehension of the content, shall be open or closed captioned"</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This places our priority on compliance instead of on our users. We really want think about it like this:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>"Ok, we’re using video. Which of our users does this affect? Well, for users who can’t see the video, we should add audio descriptions and we’ll add captions for people with hearing disabilities. Hmmm—Some of our users might not have the video player we’re asking for. We should also add a transcript of the video. Is there anyone else we might be missing?"</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This approach is user focused and, at the end of the day, that’s what accessibility is all about. It’ll also give you a framework for understanding the meaning of the guidelines when you get there.We’re going to follow ten rules when we design accessible sites:</p>
<h2 id="mcetoc_1e3ku9rr10">Ten Principles for Web Accessibility</h2>
<ol>
<li>Avoid making assumptions about the the physical, mental, and sensory abilities of your users whenever possible.</li>
<li>Your users’ technologies are capable of sending and receiving text. That’s about all you’ll ever be able to assume.</li>
<li>Users’ time and technology belong to them, not to us. You should never take control of either without a really good reason.</li>
<li>Provide good text alternatives for any non-text content.</li>
<li>Use widely available technologies to reach your audience.</li>
<li>Use clear language to communicate your message.</li>
<li>Make your sites usable, searchable, and navigable.</li>
<li>Design your content for semantic meaning and maintain separation between content and presentation.</li>
<li>Progressively enhance your basic content by adding extra features. Allow it to fall back gracefully for users who can’t or don’t wish to use them.</li>
<li>As you encounter new accessibility challenges, apply these same principles as appropriate.</li>
</ol>
<p>These principles apply to just about everything you’ll need to do to design accessibly. Of course, you’ll need to understand <em>how</em> to apply them. That’s good, because we’re just getting started.</p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Once Upon a Time</title>
        <author>
            <name>Jeremy Sydik</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://jsydik.github.io/accessibility-dojo/title-goes-here.html"/>
        <id>https://jsydik.github.io/accessibility-dojo/title-goes-here.html</id>

        <updated>2020-03-18T04:18:44-05:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://jsydik.github.io/accessibility-dojo/media/posts/1/Bulldozer-Vetsikas-BW.jpg" alt="An old bulldozer, photographed in black and white" />
                    <p>Over a decade ago, I wrote a book about web accessibility to gather together the thoughts and experiences of ten-ish years working in the field.  All in all it was a great experience—I had the opportunity to work with the fine people at <a href="https://pragprog.com" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Pragmatic Bookshelf</a>, was able to speak about digital accessibility to broad audiences, met many other professionals exploring inclusive design, and engaged with readers who enjoyed the book and became advocates of accessibility themselves.  So what happened next?</p>

                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://jsydik.github.io/accessibility-dojo/media/posts/1/Bulldozer-Vetsikas-BW.jpg" alt="An old bulldozer, photographed in black and white" />
                <p>Over a decade ago, I wrote a book about web accessibility to gather together the thoughts and experiences of ten-ish years working in the field.  All in all it was a great experience—I had the opportunity to work with the fine people at <a href="https://pragprog.com" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Pragmatic Bookshelf</a>, was able to speak about digital accessibility to broad audiences, met many other professionals exploring inclusive design, and engaged with readers who enjoyed the book and became advocates of accessibility themselves.  So what happened next?</p>

<p>My path to inclusive design started in the summer of 199x.  I wrote in <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/2153345.Design_Accessible_Web_Sites" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Design Accessible Web Sites</a>:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Back then, I was working as a student web developer and sysadmin and we needed a system for a blind user to work on a paper.  Simple enough—we had some new systems.  Just grab one, install it, add the specialized software and we're done.  I was fairly happy about the job—it was my first time through this kind of configuration and I finished with plenty of time so I added on nicer (I thought) speakers and keyboard.</p>
<p>Our user came in and started to use the system—or at least tried to use the system.  Everything started to fall apart. The keyboard was one of the newer (at the time) ergonomic keyboards, which the user had never worked with.  The speakers were an even bigger problem.  They came out of the box set to a low volume and I hadn’t thought to set them high so they could be controlled from software.  The user began to panic when the interface to the system was completely disrupted.  Two decisions that wouldn’t have usually been a problem turned the afternoon into a disaster.</p>
<p>Of course, the real problem was human, not technological.  My mistake was in my assumption about how people use computers which, of course, was how I used a computer.  I knew that blind users needed to use special software on their computers, but I didn’t consider the real difference in user experience.  Later that evening, I got curious about my web sites—seeing how much difference something as simple as a different keyboard could make, how would my sites behave for users with screen readers instead of monitors and keyboards but not mice?</p>
<p>It wasn’t pretty.  I knew that I needed to design my sites differently, but what exactly did I need to do?  It turns out that accessibility isn’t really that much about what you do—it’s a matter of how you do it.  What I really needed was information on what being accessible means and how to think from the perspectives of many kinds of users.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>So that's what happened. I went to my HCI professor and started asking questions. At the time, HCI (now usually considered UX) wasn't a prominent topic in many computer science programs, so she advised that I go speak with some cognitive psychologists. As luck would have it, the ADA officer who ran the lab I was working in, Dr. Christy Horn, was a leading advocate for the rights of persons with disabilities as well as professor of educational psychology. She was also a persistent recruiter of graduate students—which resulted (eventually) in my own pursuit of a doctorate.</p>
<p>John Lennon said it well—"Life is what happens to you while you're busy making other plans."  The book was finished shortly before I completed my master's work, Christy and I continued to work on grants to improve higher education for students with disabilities, I eventually took over operations of the lab I started in, and my spouse and I added two more children to our lives.  Things were good but certainly busy.</p>
<p>One day, a couple of years back, I got the note that all technical authors do that the run for Design Accessible Web Sites was finished and it would be going out of print.  It was around much longer than I expected, actually—better than half a decade if a great run for an edition.  Remarkably, the vast majority of the content is still relevant—there are certainly things that have become dated.  For example, I could now write the chapter on Flash in one word—"Don't."  The real question was how to get this content back out there where it could be useful to others.</p>
<p>I punted around the idea of revising a new edition, but held off.  I was finishing up my dissertation, raising my kids is always my chief priority, and then professional changes made life excessively busy for a couple of years.  More importantly, I noticed a pattern—every couple of years, a new accessibility author would put out a book, it would make its run, and then disappear into the twilight.  While I'm still very proud of the product, I'm not entirely sure that books are the best way to approach this kind of content.  Even at the time, I wrote the book a series of articles designed to be read out of order as needed in the process of professional practice.   </p>
<p>So the answer is this - a return to blog style articles for the first time in a long while.  My plan is to revisit old content from Design Accessible Web Sites, splitting, updating, and remixing as needed as well as to periodically write up new things as they become timely.  At this point there is no particular schedule or timeline, so bear with me.</p>
<p>As an aside, Design Accessible Web Sites began "It was a dark and stormy night..." (really).  My editor was <em>not at all</em> happy with this choice, but it got enough of a positive result from readers that I'll kick off this set of articles with "Once upon a time" anyway.    </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>It&#x27;s Not Polite to Flash Your Audience</title>
        <author>
            <name>Jeremy Sydik</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://jsydik.github.io/accessibility-dojo/its-not-polite-to-flash-your-audience.html"/>
        <id>https://jsydik.github.io/accessibility-dojo/its-not-polite-to-flash-your-audience.html</id>

        <updated>2020-03-17T22:35:29-05:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://jsydik.github.io/accessibility-dojo/media/posts/4/AccessMazeBW.jpg" alt="" />
                    Life is interesting sometimes. Not long ago, I was writing a tip in Design Accessible Web Sites about flicker and photosensitive epilepsy. I kind of went back and forth about whether this was a common enough issue to worry about. In the end, I decided that&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://jsydik.github.io/accessibility-dojo/media/posts/4/AccessMazeBW.jpg" alt="" />
                Life is interesting sometimes. Not long ago, I was writing a tip in Design Accessible Web Sites about flicker and photosensitive epilepsy. I kind of went back and forth about whether this was a common enough issue to worry about. In the end, I decided that it was too important to not discuss in depth.<br><br>When video flickers at the right speed, some people have seizures. The degree of the seizure varies, but to be sure, this isn’t a pleasant way to relax watching television or a web video. If you test your video for flicker problems using <a href="http://www.hardingfpa.tv" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Harding FPA</a> or TRACE Center’s <a href="https://trace.umd.edu/peat" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Photosensitive Epilepsy Analysis Tool (PEAT)</a>, you can avoid inappropriate levels of flicker. If you don’t test it, you run the risk of seriously harming some of your users.<br><br>This was exactly what happened this week when a video introduction was rolled out for the 2012 London Olympics [<a href="http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/uk_news/england/london/6724245.stm" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">BBC News: Epilepsy fears over 2012 footage</a>]. A segment in this video featured a multicolor flicker that was not tested for problems and viewers suffered from seizures. Fortunately, it appears that fewer than a dozen people reported being affected by this video (An infamous episode of Pokemon a few years back had over 500 reported seizures). I’m not as concerned about the reported numbers as by the potential damage though—in the end, 23000 people in the UK were put at risk of seizures caused by this video.<br><br>Most of us don’t worry about things like the flicker rate of our content very often. It seems like a minor factor that effects only a few people. It’s never just a few people - a small percentage of the total population is still in the thousands. It’s also not a great way to do business. London mayor Ken Livingstone had these comments:<br><br>* "If you employ someone to design a logo for you and they haven’t done a basic health check you have to ask what they do for their money" [<a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/06/07/world/europe/07olympics.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">New York Times: 2012 Olympic Logo: Sparks Precede the Flame</a>].<br>* "Who would go into a firm like that again and ask them to do that work. This is a pretty basic thing" [<a href="http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/uk_news/england/london/6727029.stm" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">BBC News: Mayor wades into 2012 footage row</a>].<br><br>These are important things to think about. As web designers, we make our livings by serving an audience. If we allow harm to come to that audience, we allow harm to come to ourselves.
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
</feed>
